

## RESEARCH STATEMENT

My research aims to help end user programmers more effectively *author*, *understand*, and *reuse* code and data through the design of new languages and program visualization tools. New declarative programming languages can raise the level of abstraction to focus on relevant domain-specific details. Improved tools can better align with and enrich end user programmers' mental models. Visualizing program state and behavior promotes program understanding, and can proactively surface surprising or incorrect results.

# **EDUCATION**

2016 - present PhD Candidate Computer Science and Engineering

SEATTLE, WA Paul G. Allen School of Computer Science & Engineering

University of Washington (UW)

Advisor: Jeffrey Heer

2016 MS COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING

SEATTLE, WA Paul G. Allen School of Computer Science & Engineering

University of Washington (UW)

Advisor: Jeffrey Heer

2014 BS COMPUTER SCIENCE

CLAREMONT, CA Harvey Mudd College (HMC)

Advisor: Ben Wiedermann

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Summer 2019 RESEARCH INTERN, ADOBE RESEARCH

SEATTLE, WA Advisors: Leo Zhicheng Liu and Wilmot Li.

Summer 2018 RESEARCH INTERN, ADOBE RESEARCH

SEATTLE, WA Interactive Repair of Tables Extracted from PDF Documents on Mobile Devices

Advisor: Leo Zhicheng Liu. Conducted research on the future of dynamic PDF documents, focusing on the analysis & reuse of tabular data for dynamic applications on mobile devices.

2013-2014 PROJECT MANAGER, CAPSTONE PROJECT, HMC COMPUTER SCIENCE DEPARTMENT

CLAREMONT, CA Visualizing and Exploring Performance Data alongside VMware

Advisor: Melissa O'Neill. Acted as project manager for a senior capstone project with

VMware in which we developed a dashboard for visualizing system performance using D3.js.

Summer 2013 UNDERGRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT, HMC COMPUTER SCIENCE DEPARTMENT

CLAREMONT, CA Visualizing the Graphical Execution of Abstract Program Traces

Advisor: Ben Wiedermann. Modified the UC Santa Barbara JavaScript Abstract Interpreter to output runtime information about the abstract program trace and implemented a tool for

visualizing program traces using D3.js.

Summer 2012 UNDERGRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT, HMC COMPUTER SCIENCE DEPARTMENT

CLAREMONT, CA Large Scale, Educational Video Games for Middle School Students

Advisor: Elizabeth Sweedyk. Developed a math-based game for the iPad that teaches children about ratios by taking advantage of the ratio-based behavior of mixing paint.

Jane Hoffswell Curriculum Vitae

# HONORS AND AWARDS

2019 ACM CHI 2019 Doctoral Consortium Award

Hopper x 1 Seattle 2019 Scholarship Award Recipient

2014 Jeff Dean - Heidi Hopper Endowed Regental Fellowship Recipient

Harvey Mudd College Computer Science Clinic Poster Award

Honorable Mention CRA Undergraduate Research Award Competition

2011-2014 Harvey Mudd College Dean's List

2010 International Baccalaureate

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

2019 Interactive Repair of Tables Extracted from PDF Documents on Mobile Devices.

Jane Hoffswell and Zhicheng Liu.

ACM Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI), 2019. doi.org/10.1145/3290605.3300523

2018 SetCoLa: High-Level Constraints for Graph Layout.

Jane Hoffswell, Alan Borning, Jeffrey Heer.

Computer Graphics Forum (Proc. EuroVis), 2018. doi.org/10.1111/cgf.13440

Augmenting Code with In Situ Visualizations to Aid Program Understanding.

Jane Hoffswell, Arvind Satyanarayan, Jeffrey Heer.

ACM Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI), 2018. doi.org/10.1145/3173574.3174106

Supporting Patient-Provider Collaboration to Identify Individual Triggers using Food and Symptom Journals. Jessica Schroeder, **Jane Hoffswell**, Chia-Fang Chung, James Fogarty, Sean Munson, Jasmine Zia. ACM Computer-Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW), 2017. doi.org/10.1145/2998181.2998276

2016 Visual Debugging Techniques for Reactive Data Visualization.

Jane Hoffswell, Arvind Satyanarayan, Jeffrey Heer.

Computer Graphics Forum (Proc. EuroVis), 2016. doi.org/10.1111/cgf.12903

Reactive Vega: A Streaming Dataflow Architecture for Declarative Interactive Visualization. Arvind Satyanarayan, Ryan Russell, **Jane Hoffswell**, Jeffrey Heer. *IEEE Trans. Visualization & Comp. Graphics (Proc. InfoVis '15)*, 2016. doi.org/10.1109/TVCG.2015.2467091

## WORKSHOP PUBLICATIONS

Spring 2019 Languages & Visualizations to Enable Effective End User Programming.

GLASGOW, UK Jane Hoffswell. ACM Human Factors in Computing Systems Extended Abstracts (CHI EA),

2019. doi.org/10.1145/3290607.3299067

Spring 2015 Debugging Vega through Inspection of the Data Flow Graph.

Cagliari, Italy Jane Hoffswell, Arvind Satyanarayan, Jeffrey Heer. Euro Vis Workshop on Reproducibility,

Verification, and Validation in Visualization (EuroRV3), 2015. doi.org/10.2312/eurorv3.20151144

Jane Hoffswell CURRICULUM VITAE

# **POSTERS**

LANGUAGES & VISUALIZATIONS TO ENABLE EFFECTIVE END USER PROGRAMMING. Spring 2019 Glasgow, UK

ACM Human Factors in Computing Systems Doctoral Consortium Poster, 2019.

VISUAL DEBUGGING TECHNIQUES FOR REACTIVE DATA VISUALIZATION. Fall 2016

SEATTLE, WA University of Washington Computer Science & Engineering Affiliates, 2016.

#### **PRESENTATIONS**

Spring 2014 VISUALIZING THE GRAPHICAL EXECUTION OF PROGRAMS FOR JAVASCRIPT ABSTRACT INTERPRETATION.

San Diego, CA Southern California Celebration for Women in Computing.

Fall 2013 VISUALIZING THE GRAPHICAL EXECUTION OF PROGRAMS FOR JAVASCRIPT ABSTRACT INTERPRETATION.

Los Angeles, CA Southern California Programming Languages and Systems Workshop.

## TEACHING EXPERIENCE

TEACHING ASSISTANT, UW PAUL, G. ALLEN SCHOOL OF COMPUTER SCIENCE & ENGINEERING 2016-2017

SEATTLE, WA Professor: Jeffrey Heer. Graded coursework, held office hours, and led tutorial sessions for

the graduate (Spring 2016) and undergraduate (Spring 2017) Data Visualization courses.

Winter 2014 TEACHING ASSISTANT, UW MASTERS IN HUMAN COMPUTER INTERACTION + DESIGN

SEATTLE, WA Professor: Jeffrey Heer. Helped to develop the course curriculum. Tutored and graded

coursework for students studying User Interface Software & Technology (Winter 2014).

TUTOR AND GRADER, HMC COMPUTER SCIENCE DEPARTMENT 2012-2014

Claremont, CA Tutored and graded for Programming Languages (SP 2014), Artificial Intelligence (SP 2014),

Software Development (SP 2013, FA 2013), and the Principles of Computer Science (FA 2012).

# LEADERSHIP AND VOLUNTEER EXPERIENCE

REVIEWER for ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2020, CHI 2017 - present

> 2019, CHI 2017), IEEE Visualization Conference (VIS 2019, VIS 2018), ACM Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology (UIST 2019, UIST 2018, UIST 2017), and Transactions

on Visualization and Computer Graphics (TVCG 2018).

GRAD, VGRAD, & POSTDOC ADVISORY COUNCIL, UW COMPUTER SCIENCE & ENGINEERING 2018 - present

SEATTLE, WA Participated as a council member of the G5PAC to discuss and address the needs of

researchers and teaching assistants in the Paul G. Allen School.

Winter 2018 HCI VISIT DAYS COORDINATOR, UW COMPUTER SCIENCE & ENGINEERING

SEATTLE, WA Organized group activities and one-on-one meetings for admitted graduate students.

Fall 2016 GRADUATE STUDENT ADMISSIONS VOLUNTEER, UW COMPUTER SCIENCE & ENGINEERING

SEATTLE, WA Reviewed graduate student admissions applications.

NEW GRADUATE ORIENTATION LEADER, UW COMPUTER SCIENCE & ENGINEERING Fall 2015

Seattle, WA Coordinated talks from current students and faculty for incoming graduate students,

organized activities for the event, and hosted the two-day orientation.

Fall 2015 PROJECT MANAGER, USLI ROCKETRY TEAM, HARVEY MUDD COLLEGE

SEATTLE, WA Founder and project manager of a NASA sponsored rocketry team for the University

Student Launch Initiative (USLI). Designed and launched a rocket with a scientific payload.